A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Catalogued Reports, Reports 17727-19980 FA739G
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Address before the Committee on Institutional Projects Abroad of the American Council on Education, Washington, D.C, November 19 (Reports 018980), 1959
  "The Ford Foundation shares with the Committee on Institutional Projects Abroad a deep interest in foreign areas and peoples, and particularly in the growing and complex relations between those peoples and the United States." [p. 1]
- A profile in appreciation, January 26 (Reports 018981), 1960
  Address at convocation honoring George N. Shuster, president of Hunter College, at Hunter College.
  Rites and ceremonies; Education, Higher -- United States
- American education's new dimension, April 9 (Reports 018982), 1960
  Based on address at installation of President Harvey M. Rice, Macalester College, St. Paul, MN, Oct 2, 1959.
  College presidents -- Minnesota; College presidents -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Administration
- Remarks at the Carleton College Dinner in Chicago, April 27 (Reports 018983), 1960
  The requirements of American education in 1960 must be considered against the background of the important national and world forces which affect us all. [p. 2]
  Education -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
- Liberal education the challenge of the '60's (Reports 018984), 1960
- Quality control in education, May 5 (Reports 018985), 1960
  "...Changes in education have been less spectacular; but now, rapid, fundamental developments are under way in education that may turn out to be as significant as the revolution in industry and technology." [p. 1]
- Personal and public responsibility, May 31 (Reports 018986), 1960
  Commencement address at Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ.
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Arizona State University; Education, Higher -- United States; Common good
- Assisting cultural activities in the United States and Europe, October 21 (Reports 018987), 1960
  Cultural relations -- International cooperation
- The universities' role in reshaping American cities, October 28 (Reports 018988), 1960
  Progress; Metropolitan areas -- United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
- Politics and purpose in higher education, February 23 (Reports 018989), 1961
  Universities and colleges -- Education, Higher -- United States
- Higher education in New York State, March 1 (Reports 018990), 1961
  Education, Higher -- New York -- United States
- Higher education in the sixties, April 15 (Reports 018991), 1961
- Address at 12th annual meeting of the National Council on Community Foundations, May 11 (Reports 018992), 1961
  "All foundations, regardless of size, scope, or limitations, bear the overall responsibility of using their resources with a high sense of purpose and in a way most truly meaningul to society." [p. 1]
- Service for the significant, May 31 (Reports 018993), 1961
  "When service to humanity is rendered from purely ideal motives it is an adornment to the human spirit. But the measure of service being equal, it is no less a contrbution to human progress if it happens to spring from less idealistic wells." [p. 1]
  Altruism; Kindness
- Morality in a free society commencement address at University of Southern California, June 8 (Reports 018994), 1961
  "Morality is one of those subjects that are easy to talk about without saying much. The concept of morality is, at best, a vague one, more suitable for oratorical rhetoric and philosophical speculation than for precise definition and analysis." [p. 1]
  Baccalaureate addresses -- University of Southern California; Ethics
- Morality in a free society commencement address at Harpur College, June 11 (Reports 018995), 1961
  Commencement address at Harpur College, Binghamton, NY
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Harpur College; Ethics
- The changing role of higher education, May 22 (Reports 018996), 1962
  "Our land-grant colleges and universities, on the other hand, can hardly expect to build on rigid tradition or to maintain the same hallowed functions. Their common, underlying tradition is one of constant change. Now, and in the years ahead, they must co
- Forces in the space age, October 9 (Reports 018997), 1962
  "As a prime example of technological acceleration, the growth of electronics is still dazzling to behold." [p. 1]
  Astronautics and civilization -- United States; Science
- Engineering in the university, October 13 (Reports 018998), 1962
  "Nowadays, dedications of academic buildings seem to be nearly as commonplace as the athletic dedications each Saturday afternoon in the fall." [p. 1]
  Universities and colleges -- United States; Engineering -- United States; Memorials
- Urban universities in perspective, November 4 (Reports 018999), 1962
  "...They have set the stage for fundamental changes in the relation of man to his fellow man -- in material, cultural, and moral terms. And in one way or another, they have all spelled change for urban universities and for higher education in general." [p
  Universities and colleges -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States; Cities and towns
- Our urbanized planet, November 19 (Reports 019000), 1962
  "Nevertheless, it is not true, as they say in New York, that "this will be a wonderful city when they finish it." Cities can be wonderful places in the course of putting literally endless finishing touches to them." [p. 1]
  Cities and towns -- Growth -- United States
- The public stake in private service, December 4 (Reports 019001), 1962
  "Without voluntary services and leadership of men like Bill Kahler, the vast array of private civic, educational, and philanthropic activities of this nation could not long survive." [p. 1]
  Voluntarism -- United States; Altruism
- New perspectives for college spirit, January 24 (Reports 019002), 1963
  "...The image of the overly nostalgic, football-addicted, intellectually-arrested son of Alma Mater is disappearing..." [p. 1]
  Universities and colleges -- Alumni and alumnae -- United States
- The educated American and the ideal of service, January 29 (Reports 019003), 1963
  "That was a call for education in the community's service -- a call that is surely applicable to any other state, or, for that matter, to any other country." [p. 2]
  Service learning -- Education, Higher -- United States
- The bridge of technology, February 1 (Reports 019004), 1963
  "Only three months ago I spoke at the dedication of another great new engineering education facility, the quadrangle at Princeton University. In the United States, we regard Princeton as a venerable university." [p. 1]
  Universities and colleges -- Trinidad and Tobago -- West Indies; Engineering -- West Indies; Memorials
- Facts and fancies about foundations, February 16 (Reports 019005), 1963
- Education: an investment in the future, April 2 (Reports 019006), 1963
- The American gray area, June 5 (Reports 019007), 1963
  Commencement address at George Washington University, Washington, D. C.
  Baccalaureate addresses -- George Washington University; Education -- United States
- The uses of talent, June 15 (Reports 019008), 1963
  Commencement address at University of Illinois, Urbana, IL.
  Baccalaureate addresses -- University of Illinois; Education -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- The dimensions of educational management, July 16 (Reports 019009), 1963
  Address at Meeting of National Association of College and University Business Officers, Pittsburg, PA.
  Education -- United States; School management and organization -- Education, Higher -- United States
- Address at Annual Dinner of the Chicago Medical School, Chicago, IL., October 10 (Reports 019010), 1963
  The American people need and expect to get more doctors -- practitioners with the latest in medical knowledge and the most advanced techniques and facilities. [p. 2]
  Education -- United States; Medical colleges -- Education, Higher -- United States
- In common cause: relations between higher education and foundations, November 13 (Reports 019011), 1963
  "No observer of higher education today can fail to realize the very great importance of the instituions you represent. As a foundation officer, I was most interested to learn that this association and two others in higher education had recently merged." [
  Education -- United States; Endowments -- Education, Higher -- United States
- Education for economic growth, November 15 (Reports 019012), 1963
  "The extraordinary ability of American enterprise to adapt to swift -- and sometimes turbulent -- social, economic, and technological change owes much to the early emergence in this country of business management as a professional calling." [p. 1]
  Education -- United States; Business education -- United States
- Diversity and progress, February 23 (Reports 019013), 1964
  "Our world is rife with conflicting ideologies, straining power blocs, and divergent standards of living. But all nations share one concept that is embodied in this college and the hundreds of other colleges and universities throughout the nation." [p. 1]
- The university in America, March 16 (Reports 019014), 1964
- The American University, May 21 (Reports 019015), 1964
- The arts in a scientific culture, June 12 (Reports 019016), 1964
  Commencement address California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, CA.
  Baccalaureate address -- California Institute of Technology; Education -- United States; Art and science -- Education, Higher -- United States
- Agenda for leadership, June 29 (Reports 019017), 1964
  "Foundations, too, are investing in the future. But the nature of our investment is quite different. While we employ funds to work toward our objectives, the real currency of foundation enterprise consists of ideas and human talent." [p. 1]
- The right to knowledge, July 12 (Reports 019018), 1964
  "An assembly concerned with education ought to concentrate on the educational aspect of this subject. But of course, the education of Negroes is entwined in the historical, social, and moral fabric of American society." [p. 1]
  African Americans -- Education -- United States
- The environmental prespective, November 6 (Reports 019019), 1964
  Institutions like the University of Missouri embody the unique characteristics of American higher education. No other nation has so effectively applied the resources of higher learning to the advancement of human welfare. [p. 1]
  College presidents -- Inauguration; Ecology
- American foundations and the common welfare, March 5 (Reports 019020), 1965
  The role of philanthropic foundation in American life is an especially appropriate subject to discuss in the company of scholars. Foundations in this country have devoted much of their efforts to the advancement and dissemination of knowledge
  Public interest; Endowments
- Within the nation's reach, April 12 (Reports 019021), 1965
  "The established dogma of Southern education has been resignation to second-best status. Under what some Southern leaders called the 'cult of easiness,' Southern colleges and universities compared themselves only with others in the region." [p. 1]
- The private sector in public affairs: how effective?, April 15 (Reports 019022), 1965
  The concept that public affairs are not exclusively government affairs is deeply rooted in our traditions. Individual men and women and a vast array of private institutions and organizations play essential roles in public affairs...
  Endowments; Public interest; Common good
- Steps toward a solution, May 8 (Reports 019023), 1965
  It took a long time for the dangers of escalating human fertility to command widespread concern. [p. 1]
  Population; Birth control
- Beyond world conflict, June 6 (Reports 019024), 1965
  "These last few months have seen American universities cast into unusual prominence. Faculty members and students have contended with the very highest levels of government on grave issues of foreign policy. And on campuses in many parts of the country, pr
  International relations; Education -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- The uses of higher education, October 8 (Reports 019025), 1965
  The opening of a new university is a call to high adventure. Those of you who are at the controls as Cleveland State University begins its journey may be proud that a long period of planning and preparation has been successfully completed. [p. 1]
  Gathering rites; Universities and colleges -- United States; Education, Higher -- United States
- Technology and timidity in education, November 19 (Reports 019026), 1965
  "Technology and education go hand in hand, and their relationship has become considerably more intimate in the last decade." [p. 1]
  Technology -- Education -- United States
- Speech on private foundations (Reports 019027), 1972
  "Foundations are private, nonprofit organizations set up as corporations or trusts, usually under state laws, to receive and distribute funds for the advancement of human welfare." [p. 1]
- The role of private philanthropy in the newly developing nations, February 24 (Reports 019028), 1960
  Private American philanthropy has long concerned itself with the problems of the less economically developed parts of the world. [p. 1]
- Family structure and dynamics of fertility control, May 9 (Reports 019029), 1966
  Lecture to Seminar on Population Dynamics, Johns Hopkins University.
  Population
- Remarks on the Foundation at Civic Center, Pasadena, CA, April 24 (Reports 019030), 1951
  The Foundation satisfies in many the traditional American love of superlatives. [p. 2]
- Address at the Victory dinner of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology Development Program, May 4 (Reports 019031), 1951
  "I would like to discuss with you this evening one of these basic shifts in the American pattern. It is a shift that already has had a great impact on our way of life, and in my opinion will have an even greater impact in the years ahead." [p. 2]
- Remarks on communism and capitalism, June 12 (Reports 019032), 1951
  "If we businessmen -- of whatever country -- want a verdict in our favor, we had better convince the jury of people all over the world that the economic system of which we are a part will do more for them than any other system..." [p. 3]
  Business; Communism; Capitalism
- Remarks at Centennial International YMCA Convention, Cleveland, OH, June 22 (Reports 019033), 1951
  "As we all know, democracy comes from two Greek words signifying power of the people. For that reason we to think of democracy primarily as a polical matter." [p. 1]
  Democracy -- United States
- Address before the National Association of Life Underwriters, Los Angeles, CA, September 19 (Reports 019034), 1951
  Let me deal first with the question of World War III. I am aware of all the dangers. [p. 2]
  Cold War
- Remarks at Rotary Club of Padena, September 26 (Reports 019035), 1951
  "Today we are painfully conscious that the river Yangtze flows down Main Street, and that the river Han in Korea also flows down Main Street, and so does the Rhine, the Seine, and the Volga." [p. 2]
- Address at Westwood Community Methodist church, Los Angeles, September 30 (Reports 019036), 1951
  "The largest obstacle to the achievement of peace is, of course, the determination of the Russian leaders to force their Godless way of life upon the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address to Automoile Old timers, Detroit, MI, October 4 (Reports 019037), 1951
  "The record of cooperation in the automotive industries is as outstanding as the record of competition, and equally important." [p. 4]
  Automobile industry and trade -- United States
- Address at Freedom House Award, October 7 (Reports 019038), 1951
  Freedom is concerned with maintenance of freedom and with the maintenance and perfection of a free society. [p. 1]
- Address at Harvard Business School Club of New York, New York City, October 9 (Reports 019039), 1951
  "...For between the end of World War II and the start of the Marshall Plan in the spring of 1948, not only had the countries of Eastern Europe fallen under Soviet sway, but also during this same period Mao Tse Tung in China, using compas and T-square mad...
  International relations; Economic assistance -- Europe
- Address at Wendell L. Willkie Memorial Program, October 18 (Reports 019040), 1951
  The people were right. In that great heart of Wendell Willkie there was a deep love for people -- the people of his home town of Rushville... [p. 1]
- Memorial address for Senator A. Vandenberg at Grand Rapids Council on World Affairs, October 19 (Reports 019041), 1951
  "Senator Vandenberg was one of those great men whose heart was for all men and who will live in the hearts of men everywhere, because he understood so deeply that the long-range self-interest of his country lay in peace, justice and freedom for all men...
- Address at New York Herald Tribune Forum, New York, NY, October 24 (Reports 019042), 1951
  Any plan to relieve tensions in the world today must take into account the hard and relentless determination of the Soviet overlords to CREATE tensions. [p. 1]
  International relations; Cold War
- Address at Los Angeles Council of Church Women, November 2 (Reports 019043), 1951
  "...In some countries any kind of peace is acceptable, but we in the free world insist that peace must be based on freedom and justice." [p. 1]
- Address at National Institute of Social Sciences, New York, NY, November 8 (Reports 019044), 1951 (Box 890)
  "To wage the peace intelligently, we must recognize the nature of the danger which surrounds us." [p. 3]
- Remarks at National Conference of Christians and Jews, November 15 (Reports 019045), 1951
  "Our greatest danger today is that we will act as a frightened people, and that the sense of insecurity that has enshrouded us will lead us to acts of desperation." [p. 1]
- Our common cause, November 28 (Reports 019046), 1951
  Address at English Speaking Union.
- Address at First International Conference of Manufacturers, New York City, December 3 (Reports 019047), 1951
  "People who have been slumbering through the centuries are not awakening and saying, "We want a better life." In Europe and here in American the great mass of pople are demanding a better life." [p. 3]
  International relations; Manufacturing industries
- Quest for peace, December 11 (Reports 019048), 1951
  Address at Institute of World Affairs, Riverside, CA.
- Address at Commonwealth Club, San Francisco, CA, December 21 (Reports 019049), 1951
  "Each of the 361 days that has come and gone since Christmas 1950 has brought with it reports and rumors of conflicts -- crises, tensions and outright warfare." [p. 1]
- Address at Ebell Club of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, CA, January 2 (Reports 019050), 1952
  "During the past quarter of a century, we have lived in a continuing atmosphere of tension. As we entered upon each year, we have been solemnly to that it was the year of decision." [p. 1]
- Address at Automobile Old timers, San Francisco, CA, January 4 (Reports 019051), 1952
  The America of the early nineteen hundreds was a very different America than that which had emerged by the mid-century of 1950. [p. 1]
- The world outlook, January 10 (Reports 019052), 1952
  Address at the Business Outlook Conference of the Los Angeles Chamber of Commerce, Los Angeles, CA.
- Address at Wellesley Club of southern California, Pasadena, CA., January 28 (Reports 019053), 1952
  "If anyone suggested a generation ago that in 1952 the most pervasive influence in our lives would be exercised by a small group of second-rate men located in Moscow, Russia, we would have thought it a huge joke." [p. 1]
- Address at Catholic Press Council of Southern California, Los Angeles, CA., February 15 (Reports 019054), 1952
  "And yet today that small group of men in the Kremlin, as a result of their determined efforts to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world, has a most pervasive influence on your daily life and mine." [p. 1]
- Address at National Conference of Christians and Jews, Los Angeles, CA., February 28 (Reports 019055), 1952
  "The basic cause of world tensions is, of course, the determination of the men in the Kremlin to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address at Foundation for Freedom Institute, UCLA., March 1 (Reports 019056), 1952
  Two world wars are still green in our memories. We are living under the threat of a third great war. We are also living with the nightmare horror of the atom bomb. [p. 1]
- Address at Philadelphia Bulletin Forum, Philadelphia, PA, March 4 (Reports 019057), 1952
  "The most obvious block to peace at the present time is, of course, the determination of the men in the Kremlin to force their tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 1]
- Address at New Hampshire Hall, University of New Hampshire, Duram, NH, March 5 (Reports 019058), 1952
  "...With many of them fighting and dying in Korea -- all these are the result of our failure, so far, to stop the drive of the Kremlin to impose their own tyrannical way of life on the rest of the world." [p. 5]
  International relations; Cold War; Campaign management
- Address at Women's National Press Club, Washington, D. C., April 16 (Reports 019059), 1952
  "Unfortunately, it is impossible for most of the peoples outside the Soviet orbit to see how these yearnings for peace and for a better tomorrow can be realized unless and until the rulers of the Russian people abandon their plans to force their tyrannica
- Peace can be now, April 29 (Reports 019060), 1952
  "There are those who believe that that drive can be halted only by another general World War. That there is danger of our becoming invloved in another World War, no one can deny." [p. 1]
- A business statesman looks at the world, May 27 (Reports 019061), 1952
  "There are those who believe that that drive can be halted only by another general World War. That there is danger of our becoming invloved in another World War, no one can deny." [p. 3]
- Address at Michigan State College, East Lansing, MI, June 8 (Reports 019062), 1952
  I am appreciative of having been invited to speak at this commencement exercise of Michigan State College for a number of reasons... [p. 1]
  Baccalaureate addresses -- Michigan State College; International relations; Cold War
- Address at General Council of Congregational Churches, Claremont, CA, June 23 (Reports 019063-001), 1952
  "Men yearn for peace but they still fear, suspect and hate some of their fellow men, particularly those who live beyond the borders of their own country." [p. 1]
- USA - not confidential, September 25 (Reports 019063-002), 1952
  Address at American Automobile Association, Washington, D. C.
  Opportunity -- United States; Women -- United States; Automobile industry and trade
- Address at Economic Club of Southwestern Michigan, St. Joseph, MI, October 30 (Reports 019064), 1952
  "The picture of 1900 would not be complete, however, unless we found how people on the other side of the tracks were living." [p. 2]
  Opportunity -- United States; Education -- United States; Economic development -- United States; International relations; Cold War
- Address at St. Andrews Society, New York City, December 1 (Reports 019065), 1952
  "The real glory of this land we live in, the underlying fact which totally justifies it, is that here men have had a constantly expanding opportunity to realize on their capacities, intellectually and spiritually as well as materially." [p. 2]
- Address at the Annual Meeting of the Institute of Life Insurance, Waldorf-Astoria, New York, December 11 (Reports 019066), 1952
  "Our capitalism is unique, too, in its capacity for growth. It doesn't just exists, it evolves, meeting changing conditions with changing methods." [p. 1]